Finding Aid for the Medical Artifacts Collection
Eskind Biomedical Library Manuscripts Collection
- 1337 Purkinje, Johann E. Death mask of Johann E. Purkinje (1787-1869) pioneer Czech experimental physiologist. Presented by Vanderbilt Faculty Member and descendant Dr. Frank Chytil at the time of his retirement in 2000. Inventoried October 22, 2018 Donated by Dr. Frank Chytil.
- 1338 Bell Jar. Large glass bell jar intended for use as a dust cover for a microscope. Glass dome with black lacquered wooden pedestal. This particular jar was used in the student laboratories of Vanderbilt School of Medicine and Hospital when it relocated from downtown Nashville to the Vanderbilt campus in 1925. Inventoried October 10, 2018. Donated by Joanne Lagerson, Sept 20, 2018.
- 1339 Student Microscope. Miniature drum compound monocular microscope, brass manufactured by Noel P. Lerebours. Paris circa 1846-50. Contained in mahogany wood case with two additional lenses and a pair of brass tweezers. Belonged to donor’s uncle Dr. Robert Weill who was Professor of Dental Surgery and later Director of the School of Dental Surgery in Paris. Inventoried October 22, 2018. Donated by Dr. Ralph Lampert (VU 1961), March 2012.
- 1340 Amputation Surgical Kit. Civil War era amputation kit manufactured by Wiegand & Snowden Philadelphia. Circa 1840 -1850. Contained in wooden case lined in purple velvet (faded to grey) Incomplete. Includes two saws, two knives, a tenaculum probe, and a tourniquet. Reportedly used by a Confederate surgeon during the Civil War. Inventoried October 22, 2018. Donated through the agency of Dr. Robert Collins.
- 1341 Apothecary jar. Glass apothecary jar. Circa 1870s. 8 .5” tall 3 3/4 “wide at base. Paper label “Confectio Sennae” Contains whole leaves. Cork stopper. Inventoried October 22, 2018
- 1342 Apothecary jar. Glass apothecary jar. Circa 1860s. 7” tall 2 .5 wide at base. Paper label “Bicarb. Potassium 1 lb.” Additional label for the Powers & Weightman Philadelphia, PA. Bottle empty but with white residue. Cork stopper. Inventoried October 22, 2018
- 1343 Apothecary jar. Glass apothecary jar. Circa 1860s. 9 1/4” tall 3 .5 wide at base. Partial paper label “Cream Tartar.” Second label illegible. Jar contains white powder. Cork stopper. Inventoried October 22, 2018
- 1344 Apothecary jar. Glass apothecary jar. Circa 1870s. 7 3/4” tall 3“ wide at base. Paper label “Extract: Quassiae” Contains ground organic material. Cork stopper. Inventoried October 22, 2018
- 1345 Apothecary jar. Glass apothecary jar. Circa 1900s. 6 .5 “tall 2” wide at base. Square glass covered gold, red, black and white label “Pot. Bitart.” Contains sunflower seeds. Ground Glass stopper. Inventoried October 22, 2018
- Box 5 59 Korean drug. Native name: "Taik Sa." A root eaten as food by the Japanese, it has a diuretic effect and is used for that purpose by the Korean medicine men.
- Box 5 60 Korean drug. Native name: "Yong Sa Mal.” Mercuric oxide used as a medicine for ulcers in various ways.
- Box 5 61 Korean drug. Native name: "Paik Chul." A root used for diarrheas, vomiting, etc. Has somewhat the effect of opium. It is a gastric tonic, increasing the appetite.
- Box 5 62 Korean drug. Mercuric oxide ointment used as a medicine for ulcers.
- Box 5 63 Korean drug. Native name: "O Juk San," (San means powder). Shredded wood, bark and twigs of unidentified plant. Decoction is used for acute abdominal colics.
- Box 5 64 Korean drug. Native name: "Chun Nam Sung." Root of a flowering plant of this name. Very poisonous. Seems to be used somewhat the way potassium iodide is used in the west. It is used, among other things, to combat glandular enlargement.
- Box 5 65 Korean drug. Native name: "Pujah" or "Tae Bu Ja.” Dried fruit of a tree. Has an intoxicating effect. Makes the whole body feel hot and heedless of cold weather. Temporarily it greatly increases a person's strength. It is poisonous in larger doses.
- Box 5 66 Korean drug. Native name: "Pal Mi Tang.” Shredded wood and other unidentified substances, decoction from which is used as an appetizer.
- Box 5 67 Korean drug. Native name: "Pan Ha." It is the seed of a grass. It has the effect of codeine, to some extent and is especially used to allay coughing.
- Box 5 68 Korean drug. Native name: "Woo Hwang Po Yong." Pills used for convulsions, green stools, fever, and vomiting in children. Instructions for usage: Grind into fine powder, dissolve in warm water or milk. Dosages to be taken three times a day. For children under 2 years: one pill; 2-3 years: two pills; and 3-5 years: three pills.
- Box 5 69 Korean drug. Red pills used for indigestion and acute gastritis.
- Box 5 70 Korean drug. Native name: "Chun Moon Tong." Root probably used as a tonic, it is said to increase strength and agility. It is helpful in lung diseases and weaknesses. Helps to check pulmonary or gastric hemorrhages.
- Box 5 71 Korean drug. Native name: "Suk Ke Whang." It is a black licorice-like substance. It is supposed to cause the hair tho become white when taken, followed by eating turnips. Often used by would-be office holders to whiten their hair in order to appear older and more dignified. Improves the blood and gives a firm texture to the flesh. Is used also for amenorrhea and do improve dimmed vision. When eaten alone it makes the eye lashes black.
- Box 5 72 Korean drug. Native name: "Sip Yon Tae Po Tang.” Supposed to be a great tonic for women.
- Box 6 73 Wilson, Owen. Gum lancet for babies' gums. Ca. 1870. Donated by Dr. Owen Wilson.
- Box 3 74 Civil War. Three amputating knives. Ca. 1850. Possibly used in the Civil War.
- Box 36 75 Medicine case of Dr. Arthur Moseley of Buckingham County, Virginia. Medicines include: 1. Compound cathartic pills, 2. Wine of Colchicum root, 3. Dover's powder, 4. Fluid extract of Valerian, 5. Tarter emetic. 6. Sulfate of morphia, 7. Ipecacuanha, 8. Antimonial wine, 9. Acetate of lead, 10. Wine of Ipecacuanha, 11. Cannabis sativa, 12. Tincture of aconite, 13. Rhubarb, 14. Extract of Hyoscyami, 15. Alum, 16. Laudanum. Case also contains an instrument for venesection with spare blades, in red morocco leather.
- Box 3 76 Civil War. Assorted surgical instruments that were possibly used in the Civil War. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 8 77 Kinlock's Urethrotome manufactured by the George Tiemann Company.
- Box 77 79 Wilson, Owen. Cupping set complete with cupping machine, suction pump, and five glass cups. It was given by Dr. Owen Wilson to Dr. Barney Brooks, who gave it to the Library for its contemplated museum. One cup still has the original valve. Contained in a wooden box. Donated by Dr. Barney Brooks.
- Box 10 80 Intubation instruments, one complete set in black leather case lined with red velvet. These instruments were introduced in America by Dr. Joseph O'Dwyer of New York who perfected the method of intubation, and marketed the instruments. A signed a card (February 26, 1894) certifying his personal inspection, is also contained in the case. Donated by Dr. T. Crowder Chapman, an alumnus.
- Box 35 81 Douglas, Richard (“Dixie”). Death mask of Dr. Douglas who was a Professor of gynecology and Abdominal Surgery at Vanderbilt University. When the library of the School of Medicine was founded in 1906, the Nashville Academy of Medicine gave the school a Donated by the private library of Dr. Douglas, which consisted of 2,500 volumes. Donated by Mrs. George Hale.
- Box 2 82 Two Saddlebags of Dr. W. E. Pratt, Buckingham, Virginia, ca. 1895. List of medicines which can still be deciphered from the labels on the glass phials: Creosote, Borax, Morphine sulphate hypodermic, bicarbonate of soda, pulv. opium, nitroglycerin, cordia, camphor, Febralgene - neuralgic acute rheumatism and fevers generally, pepsin, quinea, paregoric gentian, nux vomica, citrate of potassium, potassium arsenate, potassium iodide, bromide potash, potassium bicarbonate, ergot (fluid extract), veratrum, aconite, cinnamon, tincture of meth., salicylic acid zinc sulphate, tincture of digitalis, chloroform, peptenzym tablets, Dad's quinine pills, chocolate coated pills for rhinitis, laxoid tablets containing cascarin, hydrastinine, and other substances. Donated by Mrs. Florence Pratt, Buckingham, Va.
- Box 83 83 Eve, Paul F. Surgical instruments used by Dr. Paul Eve. Presented by Dr. Duncan Eve, Jr. instruments include: three tourniquets, a trephine, a trepanning brace, hand drill, a gynecological Hunter's speculum, and a round wooden plate with a metal attachment on the side and "P. F. Eve" scratched on the top. All ca. 1840-1870. Contained in a green painted wooden box. Note: that only the box is labeled. March 11, 1995.
- Box 84 84 Three amputation saws. Two are bow saws and one is what is known as a capital saw. All are ca. nineteenth century.
- Box 3 85 Surgical probes.
- Box 51 86 Eve, Duncan. Calculi removed by Dr. Duncan Eve, February 16, 1880. Dr. Eve together with Dr. W. F. Glenn on Nashville organized the Nashville Medical College. Dr. Eve was dean of the faculty from the beginning until 1883. (See Philip M. Hamer. The Centennial History of the Tennessee State Medical Association, 1930, pp. 383-4)
- Box 82 88 Two pair of Smellie's scissors.
- Box 10 89 Pump for aspirating fluids.
- Box 9 90 Leather case with 14 surgical clamps, manufactured by George Tiemann, New York.
- Box 82 91 Trocar, rectal, ca. 1870.
- Box 8 92 Eve, Paul F. Surgical instruments in black lacquered case lined with red silk. manufactured by Charière, Paris. Eye instruments. Some are missing. One of the instruments has "EVE" etched on the handle. Perhaps instruments belonging to Dr. Paul F. Eve. Ca. 1850.
- Box 7 94 Venesection instrument of Dr. T. Chalmers Dow. The object described appears to be a single-bladed spring-loaded lancet or scarificator.
- Box 10 95 Electrical instruments contained in wooden case.
- Box 82 99 Perkins tractors after Haygarth. Wooden handled, metal with hooked end.
- Box 18 101 Stethoscope, binaural. George P. Cammann designed the binaural stethoscope in 1851. It did not become known until 1855, when an editorial in the New York Medical Times gave it publicity. Cammann himself used it only on special occasions, for he was afraid habitual use might cause his ears to lose their natural sensitivity. Donated by Dr Bernard M. Weinstein, Nashville, March 10, 1965.
- Box 18 102 Thermometers, ten oral, 20th century. Donated by Bernard M. Weinstein, Nashville, Tennessee, March 10, 1965.
- Box 18 103 Thermometer, German make. Donated by Bernard M. Weinstein, Nashville, Tennessee, March 10, 1965.
- Box 18 104 Stethoscope, blood pressure, antique. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein, Nashville, Tennessee, March 10, 1965.
- Box 82 105 Tonsillotome, antique. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein, Nashville, Tennessee, March 10, 1965.
- Box 7 106 Ophthalmic needle holder. antique. This instrument was used to hold small needles used for eye surgery. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein, Nashville, Tennessee, March 10, 1965.
- Box 18 107 Surgeon's needle, antique. This needle has an eye which can be opened and closed by means of a slide. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein, Nashville, Tennessee, March 10, 1965.
- Box 6 109 Nasal or gynecological scissor.
- Box 18 110 Cedarwood Stethoscope. Circa 1860. Donated by Dr. Carroll Smith.
- Box 18 111 Lancets, Chinese, bronze, antique. There are three lancets, each with a unique blade. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein, Nashville, Tennessee, March 10, 1965.
- Box 7 112 Surgical needles, antique. Contained in wooden case. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein, Nashville Tennessee, March 10, 1965.
- Box 32 113 Surgical instruments from approximately 700 B.C. Found in a well near Jerusalem. Mounted on a board. Donated by Dr. Lawrence Grossman, Nashville, Tennessee, 1966.
- Box 32 114 Enema syringe (Clyster), 17th century. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein, Nashville, Tennessee, 1966.
- Box 32 115 Bookracks (two), made of Sheshamwood, hand-carved, from Sarnath, India. Donated by Dr. and Mrs. Robert L. Post. Nashville, Tennessee, 1966.
- Box 20 116 Dissecting set with knives and cannula which belonged to the late I. A. McSwain, M.D. Vanderbilt Medical School Class of 1889. Donated by Barton McSwain. M.D. September, 1968.
- Learned Building First Floor Corridor 117 Learned, A. B. Framed Vanderbilt University engineering diploma of A. B. Learned. Donated by Mr. Howard Peabody, Natchez, Mississippi, 1966.
- Box 82 118 Douglas, Richard (“Dixie”). Vaginal speculum, circa 1890, used by Dr. Dixie Douglas. Donated by Mrs. Leila Douglas Phillips, Nashville, 1967.
- Map Case Shelf 3 119 Seven Charts for acupuncture and moxa. Ca. 1970s.
- Box 33 120 Saddlebags used by Dr. Basil T. Bennett. Graduate of the University of Nashville and Vanderbilt, 1893. Donated by Dr. B. T. Bennett, Jr. (Dr. Bennett’s son),1969.
- Box 18 121 Phlebotomy instrument -- bistoury, circa 1850. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein, 1967.
- Box 21 122 Apothecary scales, early 19th century. From the estate of Dr. William McKissick Moore. Donated by Miss Bessie Moore (Dr. Moore’s daughter), 1967.
- Box 23 124 Pewter liquid measures. seven graduated in size made in Belgium in the 19th century. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein, 1969.
- Box 21 125 Nested weights (similar to Nuremberg weights), 17th century, structured so that the largest cup equals the sum of the weight of the others. The second cup is half the weight of the largest cup. The ratio continues from cup to cup. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein, 1969.
- Box 6 126 Spring-loaded lancet or single-bladed scarificator, 19th century. Donated by Dr. Amos Christie, from the collection of Mr. Stanley Horn, 1970.
- Box 32 127 Scarificator, 18th century. Contained in a red morocco case. Donated by Dr. Amos Christie, from the collection of Mr. Stanley Horn, 1970.
- Box 7 128 Gouley sound with whale bone filiform for dilating urethral strictures, ca. 1875. Donated by Dr. Harry S. Shelley, 1970.
- Box 6 129 Syringe for administering intravenous solutions, ca. 1920. Donated by Dr. Harry S. Shelley, 1970.
- Box 82 130 Recórd syringe presently used in Europe. Brass. Donated by Dr. Harry S. Shelley, 1970.
- Box 34 (In ctions Room) 131 Bausch and Lomb microscope with a movable stage, 1876. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein.
- Box 82 132 Obstetrical instruments used by Dr. William Jesse Core's great uncle, Dr. Jesse Core, Sr., from about 1840 to 1870 in Williamson County south of Franklin. Contained in a red, black, and white cotton cloth roll-up case. Donated by Dr. William Jesse Core.
- Box 6 133 Instrument case and drug kit, ca 1900. Donated by Dr. Basil T. Bennett.
- Box 15 134 Two apothecary jars, modern replicas of older ones. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein.
- Box 7 135 Urethral sound, German. Donated by Dr. Harry S. Shelley, December, 1970.
- Box 4 136 Quervain cranial rongeur forceps, with two extra blades, ca. 1900. Donated by Dr. Harry S. Shelley, December 1970.
- Box 51 140 Kampmeier, Rudolph H. Drugs used for the treatment of syphilis, prepared by Dr. Kampmeier. Donated by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier.
- Box 53 141 George P. Pilling Pneumo-Thorax machine. Donated by Dr. Palmer H. Bell.
- Box 37 146 Civil War. Surgical instruments used during the Civil War. Wooden case has inlaid brass plate which is inscribed "U.S.A. Medical Department." Donated by Dr. Rollin A. Daniel.
- Box 12 147 Briggs, William T. Ophthalmology instruments used by Dr. William T. Briggs (1828-1894), Professor of Surgery, University of Nashville. Donated by Dr. Henry Carroll Smith.
- Box 4 148 Brace for trephining. Probably 18th century.
- Box 4 149 Johnson's Uvula scissors.
- Box 6 150 Three dental forceps.
- Box 82 151 Wyeth's exsector. Used for sawing long bones, the clamp held the bone while the saw was moved to and fro, ca. 1880. John A. Wyeth had been a Cavalry man under Nathan Bedford Forrest, before studying medicine. He later started the New York Polyclinic Medical School, a post-graduate institution.
- Box 9 152 Bullet extractor.
- Box 84 153 Aneurysm needle. Used for passing a ligature around a small artery, with as little disturbance as possible to surrounding tissue. Determining from the wooden handle, it is most likely Pre-Listerian.
- Box 9 154 Surgical needle holder.
- Box 22 155 Anesthetic apparatus.
- Box 22 156 Ether mask.
- Box 3 157 Collins needle for suturing silver wire.
- Box 82 158 Ecraseur Chassigmac's design. For removal of uterine tumors and polypi. Ca. 1890. Manufactured by George Tiemann & Co.
- Box 82 159 Hand lancet, possibly used as a veterinary instrument, early 19th century. Contained in a brass case, and "Jessop" is stamped on one of the fold-out blades.
- Box 22 160 Aneurysm needle, pre-Listerian times.
- Box 22 161 Davis and Kidder electric machine ca. 1850.
- Box 82 162 Civiale lithotrite. Ca. 1860. Donated by Dr. Harry Shelley.
- Box 18 163 Obstetrical forceps. Ca. 1875.
- Box 18 164 Acupuncture set. Probably French and modern. Acupuncture instruments are still in use as they were 2,000 years ago. The principle of irritation -- counter irritation is the basis of acupuncture.
- Box 18 165 Moxibustion instrument. Ca 1960s. Punk or slow burning loose material is dropped through the handle to heat the metal bottom of the applicator to produce round burns and blisters on the skin. Oriental in origin. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein.
- Box 77 166 Cupping set, Mid 20th century. Contained in a brown vinyl, zippered case. Oriental in origin. Donated by Dr. Bernard M. Weinstein.
- History of Medicine Files 168 Lecture cards. University of Pennsylvania, 1815; Transylvania University, 1823. Contained in History of Medicine Files: under Medical Schools, Lecture Cards.
- Box 9 169 Saddlebags circa 1887 belonging to Dr. Nathaniel M. Lewis (1849-1933) who graduated from Vanderbilt in 1882 and practiced medicine in Nashville for 5 years after his graduation, and then practiced in Rutherford County. The saddlebags date from at least 1887, when he moved his practice to Rutherford Co. (per correspondence with great grandson Jay Maveety of Ashville, NC. maveety@charter.net 19 September 2013. Donated by Mr. John D. (1893-1980) and Mrs. Grace M. Lewis of Ravenwood on Wilson Pike Franklin, TN May, 1965
- Box 11 172 La Motte hydrogen ion testing set. Donated by Dr. Amos Christie, June 1977.
- Box 74 175 Video tape. Reel # 1 - History of Nutrition at Teachers College. By Orrea F. Pye. .5" EIAJ Black and White. Booklet enclosed -- "Conference on Education in Nutrition -- Looking Forward from the Past." Donated by Neige Todhunter, December, 1977.
- Box 74 176 Video tape. Reel #2: Reminiscences of Mary Swartz Rose by Clara Mae Taylor. .5EIAJ Black and White. Donated by Neige Todhunter, December, 1977.
- Box 74 177 Video tape. Reel #3: Reminiscences of Henry C. Sherman by Charles Glen King. .5 EIAJ Black and White. Donated by Neige Todhunter, December, 1977.
- Box 74 178 Video tape. Reel #4: Reminiscences of R. R. Williams by W. H. Sebrell, Jr. .5 EIAJ Black and White. Donated by Neige Todhunter, December, 1977.
- Box 30 179 Crooke's Tube. This tube was used by Dr. C. C. McClure of Nashville. Donated by Mrs C. C. McClure, and her daughter Mary E. McClure.
- Box 36 180 Box of condensers.( Dr. Harry Shelley was unable to identify the items any more than the original label on the box.) Donated by Dr. C. Richard Treadway, July 14, 1978.
- Box 78 181 Wooden microscope box, ca. 1900. Donated by C. Richard Treadway, July 17, 1978.
- Box 73 C 182 X-rays from the files of Dr. C. C. McClure, Sr., Vanderbilt's first radiologist and also non of the South's first. X-rays are of foreign bodies in nose, esophagus, stomach, vagina, etc. Donated by Mrs C. C. McClure, August, 1978.
- Box 18 183 Stethoscope. Manufactured by Bazzi-Bianchi Bowles, patented 1894. Donated by Dr. Edmund Benz, February 27, 1979.
- Box 32 184 Lancet, brass in leather-covered wooden box, probably 18th century. Donated by Dr. Edmund Benz, February 27, 1979.
- Box 38 (Microscope in Historical Coll.) 186 Microscope. Compound binocular, ca. 1860. Deposited by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier from estate of Dr. John B. Youmans, July 9, 1979.
- Box 5 187 Colorimeter specimen-holding comparison tubes. Deposited by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier from estate of Dr. John B. Youmans, July 9, 1979.
- Box 20 188 Robinson, G. Canby. Head mirror. Belonging to G. Canby Robinson. Deposited by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier from estate of Dr. John B. Youmans, July 9, 1979.
- Box 82 189 Robinson, G. Canby. Loring ophthalmoscope which belonged to G. Canby Robinson. Ca. 1880. Contained in a leather-covered wooden case. Deposited by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier from estate of Dr. John B. Youmans, July 9, 1979.
- Box 5 190 Thoma Haemacytometer, manufactured by E. Leitz. Deposited by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier from estate of Dr. John B. Youmans, July 9, 1979.
- Box 5 191 Thoma Haemacytometer, manufactured by Karl Zeiss. Deposited by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier from estate of Dr. John B. Youmans, July 9, 1979.
- Box 5 192 Potain's aspirator. Deposited by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier from estate of Dr. John B. Youmans, July 9, 1979.
- Box 20 193 Medical instruments carried in the doctor's bag of J. G. Rohrig, M. D. 1909-1919, when he "specialized." Then carried in the black bag of his brother-in-law, R. H. Kampmeier in Castle Gate, Utah, 1924-25, and in Pueblo, Colorado, 1930-32. Donated by Dr. Rudoph H. Kampmeier, November 12, 1979.
- Box 6 194 Instrument for rectal insertion for the relief of gaseous distention. Used by Mrs. John B. Youmans while in nurses' training, ca. 1920. Donated by Mrs. John B. Youmans.
- Box 1 195 Saddle bags, two, containing medicine bottles, which belonged to Dr. John Youmans' grandfather, Dr. Henry Youmans. Donated by the Youmans family.
- Safe 196 Vanderbilt University School of Medicine. Bronze Medal of Vanderbilt University School of Medicine Centennial, 1975. Donated by Dr. Harry Shelley, November 1979.
- Box 5 197 Thermometer from German medical officer's kit, W.W. II. Donated by Dr. Harry Shelley.
- Box 74 198 Videocassette. Leaders in American Medicine-- Grace A. Goldsmith, M.D. Interviewed by William J. Darby, M.D., Ph.D. Secondary subject - nutrition. 60 minutes. 3/4." Donated by W. J. Darby, January 15, 1980.
- Box 74 199 Cassette. Darby Symposium Tape #1. 60 minutes. Donated by E. N. Todhunter, January 15, 1980.
- Box 74 200 Cassette. Darby Symposium. Tape #2. 60 minutes. Donated by E. N. Todhunter, January 15, 1980.
- Box 74 201 Cassette. Darby Symposium. Tape #3. 60 minutes. Donated by E. N. Todhunter, January 15, 1980.
- Box 74 202 Cassette. Darby Symposium. Dinner Speech, 60 minutes. Donated by E. N. Todhunter, January 15, 1980.
- Box 74 203 Cassette. Lord Boyd Orr, December 1970. 60 minutes. Donated by E. N. Todhunter, January 15, 1980.
- Box 74 204 Cassette. "History of Iron, Blood, Nutrition," by E. N. Todhunter. The American Dietetic Association, 1972. 60 minutes. Donated by E. N. Todhunter, January 15, 1980.
- Box 74 205 Cassette. "Progress in Nutrition and Dietetics 1776-1976," by E. N. Todhunter. February 1976, American Dietetic Association. 60 minutes. Donated by E. N. Todhunter, January 15, 1980.
- Box 54 207 Recording reel. Dr. Elmer V. McCollum, Honors Banquet, Chemistry Department, University of Kansas, May 2, 1962. 1/4," 3 hours. Donated by E. N. Todhunter, January 15, 1980.
- Box 74 208 Recording reel. The ICNND Faculty Honors Arnold E. Schaefer. August 31, 1971. Dr. W. J. Darby, Toastmaster. 1/4," 3 3/4 IPS. Donated by E. N. Todhunter, January 15, 1980.
- Box 74 209 Recording reel. The ICNND Faculty Honors Arnold E. Schaefer. August 31, 1971. Dr. W. J. Darby, Toastmaster. Original tape, 1/4," 3 3/4 IPS. Donated by E. N. Todhunter, January 15, 1980.